Inventory of the Herbert H. Bateman Papers, 1946-1982, 1968-1982
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Optometrist Legislation, 1977-1979. (Box-folder 12:9-12)
  - Background materials, memoranda and legislative materials relating to January 1978 bill to allow optometrists to use certain drugs, 1978., 23 items. (Box-folder 12:9)
    Including copy of bill (H.R. 205), copies of newspaper clippings, undated statement by Virginia Society of Ophthalmology and Otolaryngology, and packet of information on optometrist profession.
  - Constituent correspondence, regarding H.R. 205, and, several undated copies of Bateman's form letter reply, November 1977-March 1978, n.d., 91 items. (Box-folder 12:10)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to protest against Federal Trade Commission's new regulations on advertising ophthalmic goods and services, 1978., 10 items. (Box-folder 12:11)
    Including correspondence with Or. Bernard Morewitz, who instigated the protest and State Attorney General Marshall Coleman, and draft of FTC regulation.
  - Correspondence and legislative materials relating to H.R. 1262 (1979) to allow optometrists to use eye drops, 1979., 60 items. (Box-folder 12:12)
    Items include copy of bill and voluminous letters, enclosures, and telegrams from optometrists and constituents.
  Series 135: Parental Support Bill
- Correspondence regarding Bateman's sponsorship of a bill to require parents to support children under 21 attending secondary school on a fulltime basis, 1977-1978., 2 items. (Box-folder 12:13)
  Series 136: Pan-Mutual Betting
- Background and legislative materials pertaining to Virginia's consideration of legalized pan -mutual gambling, 1977-1981., 6 items. (Box-folder 12:14)
  Including research brief and booklet from the Council of State Governments, October 1981 issue of State Legislatures, booklet opposing gambling from Indiana Council of Churches, and undated Senate bill to legalize pari-mutuel betting.
  Series 137: Parole
- Official forms and applications for ex-felons seeking to gain restoration of their civil rights, including inquiry and application by one ex-felon, 1980., 12 items. (Box-folder 12:15)
  Series 138: Patrick Henry Hospital
- Correspondence and memoranda, regarding Patrick Henry Hospital's certification of need to operate a nursing home in Isle of Wight County, 1980., 20 items. (Box-folder 12:16)
  Including Bateman's correspondence with state Health Commissioner James B. Kenley and hospital officials, and outline of hospital's request with Bateman's comments on margins.
  Series 139: Peninsula Airport Commission
- Bills and correspondence relating to efforts to amend 1946 enabling legislation for Peninsula Airport Commission, first (1975, 1979) to allow commission to issue industrial revenue bonds, note (1982) to reflect withdrawal of Williamsburg and James City County from Commission, 1975, 1979, 1982., 13 items. (Box-folder 12:17)
  Series 140: Peninsula Catholic Scholarship Fund
- Documents relating to reinstatement of Peninsula Catholic Scholarship Fund, Inc., by State Corporation Commission, September 1979., 2 items. (Box-folder 12:18)
  Series 141: Peninsula Economic Development Council
- Peninsula Economic Development Council, 1976-1982. (Box-folder 12:19-22)
  - Minutes, memoranda and other documents of Virginia Peninsula Industrial Council, September-December 1976., 15 items. (Box-folder 12:19)
    Including proposed budget list of proposed officers for 1977 and amended by-laws for Council.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and technical information relating to (unsuccessful) bid by Newport News Industrial Council (NNIC, a subsidiary of Newport News Shipbuilding Co.) to build replacement steam generators for Virginia Electric and Power Company (VEPCO) at Sunny, Virginia, 1978., 40 items. (Box-folder 12:20)
    Including voluminous correspondence between officials of NNIC and VEPCO, summary report of NNIC, and draft (undated) of Bateman's letter to VEPCO president questioning the final decision. Items also include undated notes and a report on tourism on Virginia Peninsula by Peninsula Chamber of Commerce.
  - Correspondence, minutes, and memoranda, relating to the establishment of the Peninsula Economic Development Council (PEDC), 1979., 29 items. (Box-folder 12:21)
    Items include resolutions of Progress Committee of Newport News to merge into PEDC, proposed by-laws, lists of members and officers, and minutes of initial PEDC meetings, and information on economic conditions on Peninsula.
    See also Newport News Downtown, series 123.
  - Documents of (Virginia) Peninsula Economic Development Council (VPEDC), 1980, 1982., 33 items. (Box-folder 12:22)
    Including agendas and minutes of board meetings and Director's reports, July-December 1980, summaries of VPEDC activities and marketing strategies, documents relating to July 1980 agreement between VPEDC and Peninsula Port Authority of Virginia for marketing of industrial revenue bonds, and agenda, minutes, and reports for 1982 VPEDC "Competitive Factors" workshop.
    See also Industrial Revenue Bonds, series 81.
  Series 142: Peninsula Nature and Science Center
- Spiral-bound notebook of materials on Peninsula Nature and Science Center with letter from Center president to Bateman appealing for continuation of $50,000 state appropriation, December 1977., 2 items. (Box-folder 12:23)
  Series 143: Peninsula Shipbuilders Association
- May 1978 National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) memoranda refuting a Newport News Shipbuilding and Peninsula Shipbuilders Association, challenge of election victory by United Steelworkers Union at the Shipyard, 1978-1979., 5 items. (Box-folder 12:24)
  Also includes a 9 February 1979 letter from Bateman in which he explains his support of Virginia's right to work laws, and other 1979 correspondence.
  See also Privileges and Elections Committee, series 151.
  Series 144: Pentran
- Correspondence regarding funding of Peninsula Transportation District Commission, including Bateman's January 1976 correspondence with Pentran officials regarding state funding, 1975-1976., 9 items. (Box-folder 12:25)
  Series 145: Prenatal Care
- Correspondence, memoranda and reports regarding proposed amendment to 1982-1984 budget bill for funding of specialized materials and newborn hospital care, 1981-1982., 11 items. (Box-folder 12:26)
  Including letters and facts sheets from obstetricians, and copy of October 1981 interim report of state Prenatal Services Advisory Council on high rate of infant mortality in Virginia.
  Series 146: Pine Haven Home for Adults
- Correspondence, memoranda and background material relating to Bateman's support for Pine Haven Home for Adults, Newport News, 1979-1980., 51 items. (Box-folder 12:27)
  Items include background materials on homes for adults, 1979 materials on additions to Pine Haven, and 1980 correspondence between Bateman, Pine Haven President Paul Steele and Robert Adams of the Virginia Housing Development Authority (VHDA) regarding Steele's unsuccessful application for VHDA funding support. (items grouped as originally filed which is not in strict chronological sequence).
  Series 147: Ports of Virginia
- Ports of Virginia, 1968-1981. (Box 12-13)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and statistics relating to work of Bateman's Committee of Virginia Port Authority (VPA) studying tobacco handling charges at Virginia ports, 1968-1969., 96 items. (Box-folder 12:28)
    Including correspondence of Bateman, VPA officials, tobacco company officials, officials of Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad, and of storage facilities.
    See also series on Virginia Port Authority for information of Virginia ports, series 147, 204, 219.
  - Materials relating to study of tobacco handling charges at Virginia ports, 1969, 1970-1976., 63 items. (Box-folder 12:29)
    Items contain extensive information on tobacco industry, including several industry magazines and information on tobacco industry conventions of 1971, 1974, and 1976.
    See also Tobacco Association Meetings, series 195.
  - Reports and memoranda relating to unification of Virginia ports under the Virginia Port Authority, 1969-1972., 6 items. (Box-folder 12:30)
    Items contain two copies of undated survey of funding for other Atlantic coast port agencies, 1969 report of Virginia Ports Study Commission, second draft (undated) of items recommended for unification agreement, and copy of 1972 unification agreement and exhibits between the VPA and the Norfolk Port and industry Authority.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and notes regarding Pier C and Pier 9 at the Newport News Port, 1970-1972., 36 items. (Box-folder 12:31)
    Items include Bateman's 20 May 1970 statement to VPA and other items pertaining to completion of Pier C, and materials relating to study committee (on which Bateman served) investigating reactivating the ore discharging berth (Pier 9) which the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad deactivated in June 1971.
  - Correspondence and memoranda regarding economic conditions at Virginia ports, especially the port of Newport News, 1970-1974., 48 items. (Box-folder 12:32)
    Items feature discussions of decline in shipping tonnage, proposed establishment of container ramp point at Newport News, and of railroad shipping charges.
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to ports of Virginia, 1974-1975., 36 items. (Box-folder 12:33)
    Including correspondence between Bateman and VPA and railroad officials discussing proposal to establish Newport News as container ramp point for Virginia ports, memorandum on terminal charges at Hampton Roads ports, and photocopies of acts of Assembly dealing with issuance of industrial revenue bonds.
  - Correspondence, memoranda and other documents relating to raise in tariffs for stuffing and stripping containers by Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad, 1976., 76 items. (Box-folder 12:34)
    Items consist of tariff schedules and voluminous correspondence between Bateman and officials of Port Authority and railroad ultimately (1 July 1976) resulting in withdrawal of tariff increase.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches, and newspaper articles, 1976-1977., 11 items. (Box-folder 12:35)
    Items pertain to several issues relevant to Virginia ports: (1) 1976 report on impact of Virginia ports on state economy; (2) Senator Peter Babalas's February 1977 speech and photocopy of Virginian Pilot article on continuing competition between Virginia ports; and (3) materials relating to Port Authority's request to be included in Virginia public facilities bond issue.
  - Miscellaneous materials relating to Virginia ports, 1977-1979., 50 items. (Box-folder 13:1)
    Including 1978 marketing analysis of factors affecting container cargo growth, copies of documents sent to Federal Maritime Commission Illustrating damage to Virginia ports by the South Atlantic-North Europe Rate Agreement (SANE), documents relating to Norfolk Bulk Liquid Storage Terminal, and assessments of competitiveness of Virginia ports.
  - Two copies of progress report to Virginia ports and Port Authority Study Commission by Booz, Allen & Hamilton, 5 July 1979., 6 items. (Box-folder 13:2)
  - Correspondence, statistics and photocopies from newspapers relating to Newport News Marine Terminal, 1979., 23 items. (Box-folder 13:3)
    Items include correspondence with state Senator Alan Diamonstein, Chairman of the Peninsula Ports Authority of Virginia and officials of Lavino Shipping Company, operators of the Marine Terminal, discussing such matters as the possible location of a latex processing plant and storage facility at the terminal.
  - Twelfth Annual Inspection Report of the Port of Newport News, 1 May 1978., 1 item. (Box-folder 13:4)
  - Preliminary report of study to investigate financial matters relating to the Virginia ports and Port Authority for the Virginia Ports and Port Authority Study Commission, 21 December 1978, by a transportation consulting division, with January 1979 commentary by VPA Commissioner, 1978-1979., 2 items. (Box-folder 13:5)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and bulletins relating to miscellaneous issues affecting Virginia ports especially the port of Newport News, 1979-1981., 42 items. (Box-folder 13:6)
    Items include correspondence of Newport News Mayor Joseph C. Ritchie, VPA Commissioner Robert Bray, other Port Authority officials and Congressman Paul Trible, regarding disadvantages of the Port of Newport News, proposals to enhance competitiveness, and the lease of the port terminal. Mayor Ritchie (29 March 1979) complained to Commissioner Bray of the VPA's treatment of Newport News, and to Bateman (12 April 1979) of possible conflict of interest by VPA member who was also a board member of Norfolk's Port Authority.
  Series 148: Post-Session, 1976, 1978-1980, 1982
- Post-Session, 1976, 1978-1980, 1982. (Box-folder 13:7-14)
  - Post-Session, 1976., 10 items. (Box-folder 13:7)
    Copies of several acts approved during the 1976 Assembly session and incorporated into the code of Virginia, including copy of Appropriations Act.
  - Post-Session, 1978., 1 item. (Box-folder 13:8)
    Digest of acts of Assembly of 1978 regular session.
  - Post-Session, 1979., 1 item. (Box-folder 13:9)
    Summary of the regular 1979 legislative session of the Virginia General Assembly.
  - Post-Session, 1980. (Box-folder 13:10-11)
    - Copy of a bill from 1980 regular session, photocopies of 9 March 1980 article from Newport News Daily Press on final day of regular session, summary of 1980 regular session, and two copies of digest of acts of Assembly of 1980 regular session, 1980., 9 items. (Box-folder 13:10)
    - Legislative materials from General Assembly post-session, 1980., 32 items. (Box-folder 13:11)
      Including copies of several acts, summary of legislative action affecting higher education, "Weekly Patron Reports" of 18 March, 27 March, and 9 April detailing action on Bateman sponsored bills, numerical summary of regular session, list of bills not yet signed by Governor, and copy of appropriations bill for fiscal year 1981-1982.
  - Post-Session, 1982. (Box-folder 13:12-14)
    - Amendments to H.R. 30 (Appropriations bill) by Senate Finance Committee, 7 March 1982, floor amendments to H.R. 30, and joint conference committee report on H.R. 30, 13 March 1982, 1982., 15 items. (Box-folder 13:12)
    - Legislative papers relating to 1982 General Assembly post-session, 1982., 18 items. (Box-folder 13:13)
      Including summary of regular session, digest of acts of Assembly of the regular session, "Weekly Patron Report" of 17 March 1982 detailing, action on Bateman-sponsored bills, and analysis of 1982-1984 transportation funding.
    - Legislative materials relating to General Assembly post-session, 1982., 19 items. (Box-folder 13:14)
      Including tables and summaries of major budget and tax issues of regular session, weekly patron reports and approved bill reports of 1 April, 8 April, 14 April, and 3 May 1982, and copy of address by Governor Charles Robb to agency heads, 9 June 1982.
  Series 149: Pre-Filed Bills, 1980
- Legislative papers for 1980 General Assembly session, 1980., 22 items. (Box-folder 13:15)
  Including copies of House documents on Juvenile Court-Public School State Task Force and on Medicaid medical care, Senate documents on law Enforcement training in Virginia and on Air Pollution Study Commission, and copies of House bills 4-9 and Senate bills 8-15.
  Series 150: Pre-Sessions, 1980-1981
- Miscellaneous correspondence pertaining to preparations for 1980 General Assembly session, October-December 1979, 1980-1981., 8 items. (Box-folder 13:16)
  Most items have no discernible relevance to legislative matters. Also contains photocopy of Bateman's completed questionnaire about priorities for 1981 session.
  Series 151: Privileges and Elections Committee
- Draft and copy of Bateman's 27 December 1979 letter to Senator Douglas Wilder requesting assignment to privileges and elections committee, and copy of 1979 decision by Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals regarding Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock challenge of union election at the shipyard, 1979., 5 items. (Box-folder 13:17)
  Series 152: Procurement Bill
- Legislative papers and other materials regarding proposed 1982 Virginia Public Procurement Act, including copy of bill and position paper by the consulting Engineers Council of Virginia, 1982., 7 items. (Box-folder 13:18)
  See also Senate Bills, 1982; series 173.
  Series 153: Products Liability
- Products Liability, 1977-1979. (Box-folder 13:19-23)
  - Materials relating to work of joint subcommittee studying product liability laws (on which Bateman served), 977., 31 items. (Box-folder 13:19)
    Including copy of joint resolution requesting the committee, notes on July 1977 committee hearing, and packet of information from the insurance information institute.
  - Information forwarded to joint subcommittee members on product liability laws, August 1977., 7 items. (Box-folder 13:20)
    Including background report on statistical and rating procedures, position paper of Defense Research Institute, article on insurance pricing, review of 1977 Oregon law, and membership list of Industry Advisory Committee of Virginia Market Assistance Program.
  - Background papers and memoranda on products liability insurance, 7 items. (Box-folder 13:21)
    Including copy of paper presented at American Bar Association Convention, memoranda on Virginia liability insurance laws by American Insurance Association (AIA) and AIA product liability legislative package.
  - Correspondence, memoranda and reports related to study of product liability laws, 1977-1978., 29 items. (Box-folder 13:22)
    Including letters and reports from insurance industry representatives, summary of final report of the Federal Interagency Task Force on Product Liability, American Machine Tool Distributors Association publication, A State Legislator's Guide to Product Liability Problems, and joint industry committee on product liability data sources draft.
  - Materials relating to study of products liability law, 1978-1979., 48 items. (Box-folder 13:23)
    Including copies of several September 1978 bills, copies of addresses, articles and memoranda collected and distributed by Delegate George E. Allen, Jr.
  Series 154: Proposition 13
- Proposition 13, 1978-1979. (Box-folder 13:24-26)
  - Newspaper and magazine articles, memoranda and correspondence regarding California's "Proposition 13" limiting state spending and taxes and its possible adoption in Virginia, 1978., 43 items. (Box-folder 13:24)
    Including several issues of State Legislatures, background material on tax limits in other states, and memo from a state economist.
  - Correspondence, bulletins, and reports on "Proposition 13" tax and spending limitations, 1978-1979., 27 items. (Box-folder 13:25)
    Including several news releases from the Virginia taxpayers Association, September 1978 issue of State Legislatures, November 1978 bulletin, "Tax Revolt Digest," and several drafts of January 1979 report by state Revenue Sources and Economic Commission.
  - Miscellaneous materials relating to proposition 13 and tax limitation, 1979., 23 items. (Box-folder 13:26)
    Including proposed Senate Joint Resolution embodying the principle, tables and graphs showing taxation in Virginia, January 1979 working paper on real property tax levies and Bateman's 12 March 1979 letter explaining to a constituent why he voted against proposed constitutional amendment to limit state spending.
  Series 155: Public Employees
- Public Employees, 1968-1980. (Box-folder 14:1-3)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and booklets pertaining to miscellaneous issues involving state employees, 1968-1980., 44 items. (Box-folder 14:1)
    Issues include employee compensation, workmen's compensation laws, proposed salary increases for specific positions (especially commonwealth attorneys), the Intergovernmental Personnel Act, and Virginia's Blue Cross/Blue Shield Plan.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and articles relating to public employees retirement benefits, 1968-1978., 21 items. (Box-folder 14:2)
    Including letters from Virginia Education Association officials, and correspondence with Boyd F. Collier, Director of Virginia's Supplemental Retirement System, regarding Bateman constituents.
    See also Retirement, series 162.
  - Correspondence and memoranda, and minutes of meetings relating to work of joint subcommittee studying grievance procedures, 1978., 29 items. (Box-folder 14:3)
    File includes minutes of 9 September 1978 and 4 October 1978 meetings and correspondence from Virginia College and University Employees regarding grievance procedures.
  Series 156: Public Employees-Collective Bargaining
- Public Employees-Collective Bargaining, 1970-1979. (Box-folder 14:4-11)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and background materials relating to unionization of public employees, 1970-1973., 18 items. (Box-folder 14:4)
    Including 1970 opinion of Attorney General Andrew Miller on conditions of teachers negotiations with local school boards, two copies of 1970 council of state governments booklet on state-local employee labor relations, copy of 1971 (federal) state public labor-management relations Act, 1971 booklet on employee relations in state and local government by the Institute of Government of the University of Virginia, and December 1972-January 1973 constituent correspondence supporting the professional negotiation bill.
    See also Right to Work Law, series 164.
  - Correspondence and legislative documents, January 1973-February 1974., 62 items. (Box-folder 14:5)
    Items relate to bills to allow and regulate collective bargaining for public employees, including copies of bills (S. 906 and H.R. 1891), January 1974, amendments to bills and commentaries on them from constituents and from such organizations as the Virginia Manufacturers Association, copy of (January 1974) Proposed collective bargaining bill from the Newport News School System, copy of H.R. 550, 1974-1975, and recommendations of the (federal) advisory state-wide Task Force on Uniform Employee Selection Guidelines, October 1973.
  - Background materials relating to collective bargaining for public employees, 1974., 6 items. (Box-folder 14:6)
    Including March 1974 issue of the Wake Forest Law Review, newsletter and memorandum from Virginia Conference of the American Association of University Professors, and October 1974 publication by the Virginia Association of School Executives on Collective Bargaining and Virginia Schools.
  - Background materials on public employee collective bargaining, 1974-1975., 8 items. (Box-folder 14:7)
    Including booklet on legislation likely to be introduced in 1975 Assembly session, copy of 1975 bill, 1975 interim report of the commission. to study the rights of public employees, 1975 booklet on Public Sector Labor Relations, and March 1975 excerpt from the Congressional Record.
  - Materials on public employees collective bargaining received at April 1975 conference on municipality-employee problems, 1975., 8 items. (Box-folder 14:8)
    Including conference working paper, program and addresses and papers presented by officials from Texas, Massachusetts, and Hawaii.
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and other materials relating to collective bargaining for Virginia public employees, especial ly teachers, 1975-1976., 52 items. (Box-folder 14:9)
    File includes correspondence between Bateman and Newport News School Board Chairman M. M. Overman, copy of address by Andrew Miller, several copies of a 1976 bill, and 29 January 1976 memoranda by Bateman sent to all members of the Senate with responses from several state senators, including Madison Marye, Richard Boucher, Elliot Schewel, and Peter Babalas.